<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Introduction to as3commons-metadata</title>
		<author email="roland@stackandheap.com">Roland Zwaga</author>
	</properties>
	<body>

		<section name="Introduction">
			<p>AS3Commons-metadata aims to make it easier for developers to work with custom metadata annotations in actionscript source code.</p>
			<p>There are two main interfaces in this library:</p>
			<ul>
				<li><code>IMetadataProcessorRegistry</code> - A centralized registry for <code>IMetadataProcessors</code> that can decide which processors will be used for which classes or instances.</li>
				<li><code>IMetadataProcessor</code> - Implementations that contain the actual logic that will be associated with certain metadata annotations.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>The <code>IMetadataProcessorRegistry</code> interface looks like this:</p>
			<div class="source">
			        <pre>public interface IMetadataProcessorRegistry {
	function addProcessor(processor:IMetadataProcessor):void;
	function getProcessorsForMetadata(metadataName:String):Vector.&lt;IMetadataProcessor&gt;;
	function process(target:Object, params:Array=null):*;
	function removeProcessor(processor:IMetadataProcessor):void;
}</pre></div>
		<p>The addProcessor() and removeProcessor() methods speak mostly for themselves. They register or unregister a specified <code>IMetadataProcessor</code> with the registry.<br/>
		Once any processors have been added the <code>IMetadataProcessorRegistry</code> will be able to invoke these processors on any object instances or classes passed to its <code>process()</code> method.<br/>
		The <code>process()</code> method can also receieve an optional <code>Array</code> of extra parameters which will be passed into each <code>IMetadataProcessor.process()</code>  invocation.<br/>
		The <code>IMetadataProcessorRegistry</code> implementation will require some kind of mechanism to examine the specified objects for the existence of metadata. AS3Commons-metadata provides three reference
		implementations that use AS3Commons-reflect, Spicelib Reflect and Flash's native describeType() method do perform this task.</p>
		<p>The <code>IMetadataProcessor</code> interface itself is even smaller:</p>
		<div class="source"><pre>public interface IMetadataProcessor {
	function get metadataNames():Vector.&lt;String&gt;;
	function canProcess(metadataName:String):Boolean;
	function process(target:Object, metadataName:String, params:Array=null):*;
}</pre></div>
		<p>The <code>metadataNames</code> property indicates one or more metadata annotations that this prcoessor needs to be associated with.<br/>
		If the decision process is slightly more complex, the <code>canProcess()</code> method may be used by an <code>IMetadataProcessorReistry</code> implementation as well,
		perhaps the ability to perform its task by an <code>IMetadataProcessor</code> is depenendent on some kind of application state. In that case the <code>canProcess()</code>
		offers some greater flexibility.</p>
		<p>The <code>process()</code> method contains the actual business logic that is associated with the metadata annotations. The first argument is the instance that is annotated
		with the metadata that is specified by the second argument. The third argument is optional and may be used by an <code>IMetadataProcessorRegistry</code> to pass extra parameters to
		each <code>IMetadataProcessor</code>. For example, the <code>AS3ReflectMetadataProcessorRegistry</code> and <code>BytecodeMetadataProcessorRegistry</code> will pass in a <code>Type</code>, <code>Method</code>, <code>Property</code>, 
		<code>Accessor</code> or <code>Constant</code> instance. The <code>SpicelibMetadataProcessorRegistry</code> will pass in either a <code>ClassInfo</code>, <code>Method</code> or <code>Property</code> instance.<br/>
		The <code>DescribeTypeMetadataProcessorRegistry</code> simply passes in the XML node containing the reflection data for the specific member or class that contains the annotation.</p>
		<subsection name="IMetadataProcessor example">
			<p>Let's say certain classes in a project have been annotated with custom <strong>[Validated]</strong> metadata, each of these instances need to be fed into a ValidationManager instance upon instantiation.</p>
			<p>The metadata procesor responsible for doing so could be implemented like this:</p>
			<div class="source"><pre>public class ValidatedMetadataProcessor extends AbstractMetadataProcessor {
	private var _validationManager:IValidationManager;

	public function ValidatedMetadataProcessor(validationManager:IValidationManager) {
		super();
		_validationManager = validationManager;
		metadataNames[metadataNames.length] = "Validated";
	}
			
	public function process(target:Object, metadataName:String, params:Array=null):* {
		_validationManager.register(instance);
	}
}</pre></div>
		<p>The example extends the <code>AbstractMetadataProcessor</code> convenience base class provided by as3commons-metadata. But it is, of course, not required to extend this.</p>
		<p>Another example would be a processor that replaces registered class aliases with an alternative class. The implementation of such a procesor could look like this:</p>
			<div class="source"><pre>public class RemoteClassReplacerMetadataProcessor extends AbstractMetadataProcessor {

	public function RemoteClassReplacerMetadataProcessor() {
		super();
		metadataNames[metadataNames.length] = "RemoteClass";
	}
			
	public function process(target:Object, metadataName:String, params:Array=null):* {
		var classAlias:String = getClassAlias();
		var alternativeClass:Class = getAlternativeClass(classAlias);
		registerClassAlias(classAlias, alternativeClass);
	}
	
	protected function getClassAlias():String {
		//logic ommitted
	}

	protected function getAlternativeClass():Class {
		//logic ommitted
	}
}</pre></div>
		</subsection>
		</section>

		<section name="Reference implementations">
			<p>AS3Commons-metadata offers a few <code>IMetadataProcessorRegistry</code> reference implementation. The AS3Commons encourages developers to create their own though.<br/>
			The <code>AS3ReflectMetadataRegistry</code> uses the AS3Commons-reflect library to determine the various bits of metadata that may or may not be part of a speciic class.<br/>
			When metadata is encountered that has been registered in the <code>AS3ReflectMetadataRegistry</code> it will invoke the <code>process()</code> method on each <code>IMetadataProcessor</code>
			that is associated with this metadata.</p>
			<p>The <code>SpicelibMetadataRegistry</code> is very similar, the only difference is that internally it uses the Spicelib Reflect library to retrieve the class information.<br/>
			These two implementations are meant to show how the reflection logic can be abstracted and how easily a reflection library can be swapped out.<br/>
			For completion sake, the <code>DescribeTypeMetadataRegistry</code> is also offered. This implementation doesn't depend on any thrid-party reflection library but simple uses the native <code>describeType()</code>
			output to retrieve and examine the class information.</p>
			<p>Lastly, there is the <code>BytecodeMetadataRegistry</code>, this showcases how metadata processing doesn't necessarily need to be done on instances, but can be done on classes as well.<br/>
			This implementation uses the <code>ByteCodeType.metaDataLookup</code> property to find any classes that have been annotated with metadata that has been registred in the <code>BytecodeMetadataRegistry</code>.<br/>
			If one or more class names have been found it invokes its <code>IMetadataProcessors</code> as usual, only now it will pass in a <code>Class</code> object into their <code>process()</code> methods instead of
			an instance of that class.<br/>
			This implementation assumes that before its <code>execute()</code> method is invoked <code>BytecodeType.metadataLookupFromLoader()</code> has been invoked.</p>
		</section>
		
		<section name="Working with IMetadataProcessorRegistries">
			<p>Here's a very simple example of how to integrate an <code>IMetadataProcessorRegistry</code> instance into an application. Suppose you have an object factory that is responsible for creating and configuring certain types.<br/>
			This could look something like this:</p>
			<div class="source"><pre>public class MyClassFactory extends ClassFactory {
	
	private var _metadataRegistry:IMetadataProcessorRegistry;

	public function MyClassFactory() {
		super();
	}

	public function get metadataRegistry():IMetadataProcessorRegistry {
		return _metadataRegistry;
	}

	public function set metadataRegistry(value:IMetadataProcessorRegistry):void {
		_metadataRegistry = value;
	}

	override public function newInstance():* {
		var instance:MyComplexClass = new MyComplexClass();
		//creation logic omitted...
		_metadataRegistry.process(instance);
		return instance;
	}
}</pre></div>
			<p>So, after creation the instance will be examined by the <code>IMetadataProcessorRegistry</code> and processed accordingly. Obviously this is a very simplified example, but hopefully it shows off how to combine an <code>IMetadataProcessorRegistry</code>
			with other application logic.</p>
			<p>Another usage example would be to inject an <code>IMetadataProcessorRegistry</code> into a <code>IStageObjectProcessor</code>, as defined in the <a href="http://www.as3commons.org/as3-commons-stageprocessing/index.html" target="_blank">AS3Commons-stageprocessing</a> library.<br/>
			Such a stage processor could look like this:</p>
			<div class="source"><pre>public class MetadataStageObjectProcessor implements IStageObjectProcessor {

	private var _metadataRegistry:IMetadataProcessorRegistry;

	public function MetadataStageObjectProcessor() {
		super()
	}

	public function get metadataRegistry():IMetadataProcessorRegistry {
		return _metadataRegistry;
	}

	public function set metadataRegistry(value:IMetadataProcessorRegistry):void {
		_metadataRegistry = value;
	}

	public function process(displayObject:DisplayObject):DisplayObject {
		_metadataRegistry.process(displayObject);
		return displayObject;
	}
}</pre></div>
			<p>So in this case each display object that gets added to the stage (and is approved by the StageObjectProcessorRegistry's IObjectSelector) will be processed by the <code>IMetadataProcessorRegistry</code>.</p>
			<p>And that is all there is to it!</p>
		</section>
		
		<section name="The GenericMetadaProcessor">
			<p>To avoid having to implement the <code>IMetadataProcessor</code> for all processors (perhaps there are existing processors that you do not have source code access to) as3commons-metadata provides the <code>GenericMetadataProcessor</code>.<br/>
			This is an <code>IMetadataProcessor</code> implementation that is capable of wrapping an arbitrary object that is capable of processing metadata.<br/>
			The constructor for this <code>GenericMetadataProcessor</code> looks like this:</p>
			<div class="source"><pre>function GenericMetadataProcessor(wrappedMetadataProcessor:Object, methodName:String="process", applicationDomain:ApplicationDomain=null, namespace:String=null)</pre></div>
			<p>The first parameter is, naturally, the object that will be wrapped by the <code>GenericMetadataProcessor</code>, the second parameter is the method that will invoked when the <code>GenericMetadataProcessor.process()</code> method is invoked.<br/>
			The third parameter is an optional <code>ApplicationDomain</code> that the wrapped object might live in. It defaults internally to the current domain. And the last parameter is an optional custom namespace for the wrapped method.</p>
			<p>The metadata names that the wrapped object should be invoked for can then be added to the <code>GenericMetadataProcessor.metadataNames</code> property.</p>
			<p>Internally the <code>GenericMetadataProcessor</code> will inspect the wrapped object's process method signature and look for parameters of type <code>Object</code>, <code>String</code> and <code>Array</code>. Not all of theese parameters need to
			exist. If the given method only expects an <code>Object</code> then only this parameter will be used during invocation.</p>
			<subsection name="The MetadataMetadaProcessor">
				<p>As an addition to the <code>GenericMetadataProcessor</code> there is also the <code>MetadataMetadaProcessor</code>. This is an <code>IMetadataProcessor</code> implementation that inspects classes that have been annoated with the <strong>[MetadataProcessor]</strong> metadata.<br/>
				It looks for the <strong>[MetadataProcessor(metadataNames='MyMetadata,MyOtherMetadata')]</strong> to determine which metadata will will trigger this procssor. By default it will assume that the process method is called <strong>'process'</strong>. If this is not the case then the
				correct name can be added like this: <strong>[MetadataProcessor(metadataNames='MyMetadata,MyOtherMetadata', methodName='myCustomProcessMethod')]</strong>.<br/>
				The <code>MetadataMetadaProcessor</code> holds a reference to an <code>IMetadataProcessorRegistry</code>, when it is invoked for an object that is annotated with the <strong>[MetadataProcessor]</strong> it will create a <code>GenericMetadataProcessor</code> for the given instance and
				register this with its <code>IMetadataProcessorRegistry</code>.
			</subsection>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>

