<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Introduction to as3commons-bytecode</title>

    <author email="scab@dds.nl">Roland Zwaga</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="How it works">
    	<p>AS3Commons-stageprocessing offers a convenient registry system for <code>IStageObjectProcessor</code> implementations. An <code>IStageObjectProcessor</code> is meant
    	to 'post-process' a display object that has been added to the stage.<br/>
    	To keep the system as un-intrusive as possible an <code>IStageObjectProcessor</code> is registered with an associated <code>IObjectSelector</code> implementation.<br/>
    	This <code>IObjectSelector</code> decides if a <code>DisplayObject</code> that was added to the stage will be processed or not. Each <code>IObjectSelector</code> can be
    	associated with one or more <code>IStageObjectProcessors</code>.
    	<code>IObjectSelectors</code> in their turn can be associated with a certain <code>DisplayObject</code> that is considered as a 'root view'.<br/>
    	That way different areas of the stage can be associated with different <code>IObjectSelectors</code> and <code>IStageObjectProcessors</code>.
    	</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Setting things up">
    	<p>First of all, an instance of <code>FlashStageObjectProcessorRegistry</code> will need to be created and associated with the current stage.
    	<div class="source"><pre>var registry:FlashStageObjectProcessorRegistry = new FlashStageObjectProcessorRegistry();
registry.stage = stage;
</pre></div>
	Where 'stage' is a valid reference to the current stage, of course.</p>
	<p>In Flex 4 the stage can be assigned like this:
    	<div class="source"><pre>var registry:FlashStageObjectProcessorRegistry = new FlashStageObjectProcessorRegistry();
registry.stage = FlexGlobals.topLevelApplication.stage as Stage;
</pre></div>
    	</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Creating an IObjectSelector implementation">
    	<p>Creating an <code>IObjectSelector</code> is very straighforward, the interface contains only one method:
    	<div class="source"><pre>public interface IObjectSelector {
  function approve(object:Object):Boolean;
}</pre></div>
	So, a simple implementation that checks for certain package names could look like this:
    	<div class="source"><pre>public class MyObjectSelector implements IObjectSelector {
  public function approve(object:Object):Boolean {
    var className:String = getQualifiedClassName(object);
    return (className.substring(0,14) == "com.myclasses.");
  }
}</pre></div>
    	</p>
    	<p>As3Commons-stageprocessing already offers these implementations for default usage:<br/>
		<ul>
			<li><a href="asdoc/org/as3commons/stageprocessing/impl/selector/ClassNameBasedObjectSelector.html" target="_blank">ClassNameBasedObjectSelector</a></li>
			<li><a href="asdoc/org/as3commons/stageprocessing/impl/selector/ComposedObjectSelector.html" target="_blank">ComposedObjectSelector</a></li>
			<li><a href="asdoc/org/as3commons/stageprocessing/impl/selector/NameBasedObjectSelector.html" target="_blank">NameBasedObjectSelector</a></li>
			<li><a href="asdoc/org/as3commons/stageprocessing/impl/selector/PropertyValueBasedObjectSelector.html" target="_blank">PropertyValueBasedObjectSelector</a></li>
			<li><a href="asdoc/org/as3commons/stageprocessing/impl/selector/TypeBasedObjectSelector.html" target="_blank">TypeBasedObjectSelector</a></li>
		</ul>
    	</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Creating an IStageObjectProcessor implementation">
    	<p>The <code>IStageObjectProcessor</code> interface is equally brief:
    	<div class="source"><pre>public interface IStageObjectProcessor {
  function process(displayObject:DisplayObject):DisplayObject;
}</pre></div>
	</p>
	<p>Let's imagine a processor that assigns a dataprovider to certain list components that are added to the stage:
    	<div class="source"><pre>public class MystageObjectProcessor implements IStageObjectProcessor {
  public function process(displayObject:DisplayObject):DisplayObject {
    if (displayObject is List) {
      List(displayObject).dataProvider = ['option 1', 'option 2', 'option 3'];
    }
  }
}</pre></div>
    	</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Registering the IStageProcessor with the IObjectSelector">
    	<p>Now to register the two implementations takes one line of code:
    	<div class="source"><pre>registry.registerStageObjectProcessor(new MystageObjectProcessor(), new MyObjectSelector());</pre></div>
    	</p>
    	<p>After all the necessary registrations have been performed its time to activate the <code>FlashStageObjectProcessorRegistry</code>:
    	<div class="source"><pre>registry.initialize();</pre></div>
    	This will let the <code>FlashStageObjectProcessorRegistry</code> loop recursively through all the display objects that are already present
    	on the stage and let them be approved and/or processed by the registered <code>IObjectSelectors</code> and <code>IStageObjectProcessors</code>.
    	</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Registering the IStageProcessor with an IObjectSelector and a custom root view">
    	<p>The <code>registerStageObjectProcessor()</code> method takes a third optional argument of type <code>DisplayObject</code>. This <code>DisplayObject</code>
    	instance will be regarded as the root for the specified <code>IObjectSelectors</code> and their associated <code>IStageObjectProcessors</code>.<br/>
    	In other words, only <code>DisplayObjects</code> that have this root as their parent will be approved and/or processed by these specific <code>IObjectSelectors</code> and their associated <code>IStageObjectProcessors</code>:
    	<div class="source"><pre>registry.registerStageObjectProcessor(new MystageObjectProcessor(), new MyObjectSelector(), registry.stage.getChildAt(4));</pre></div>
    	</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Controlling the order that IStageObjectProcessors will be executed">
    	<p>To be able to determine in what order <code>IStageObjectProcessors</code> will be executed, a processor can optionally implement the <code>IOrdered</code> interface:<br/>
    		<div class="source"><pre>public interface IOrdered {

 function get order():int;

 function set order(value:int):void;

}</pre></div>
	The actual order can be interpreted as prioritization, with the first object (with the lowest order value) having the highest priority. When collections are sorted that contain objects that do not implement the IOrdered interface first the IOrdered implementations will be sorted with the lowest order value first, after that the remaining objects will be concatenated unordered.
    	</p>
    </section>
    <section name="The IStageObjectDestroyer interface">
    	<p>The <code>IStageObjectDestroyer</code> interface extends the <code>IStageObjectProcessor</code> interface and is meant to be invoked when an object is removed from the stage.<br/>
    	Just like its counterpart, the interface is a simple one:
    	<div class="source"><pre>public interface IStageObjectDestroyer {
	  function destroy(displayObject:DisplayObject):DisplayObject;
}</pre></div>
	Right after an object has been removed the <code>destroy()</code> method will be invoked.<br/>
	An <code>IStageObjectDestroyer</code> can be used to undo the logic of an <code>IStageObjectProcessor</code>. For instance, a processor might add event listeners, whereas a destroyer will remove them.
	</p>
	<subsection name="Turning off the stage destroyer functionality">
		<p>When the <code>IStageObjectDestroyer</code> functionality isn't desired at all it is possible to turn it off completely by setting the <code>useStageDestroyers</code> property
		on the <code>IStageObjectProcessorRegistry</code> to false:<br/>
		<div class="source"><pre>registry.useStageDestroyers = false;</pre></div>
		</p>
	</subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
