<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Welcome to as3commons</title>
		<author email="mp@yoolab.com">Martino Piccinato</author>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="Welcome to as3-commons">
			<p>
				The AS3Commons project is dedicated to one principal goal: creating and
				maintaining reusable ActionScript 3.0 components. This is a place
				for collaboration and sharing, where developers from throughout the
				community can work together on projects to be shared.
			</p>
			<p>
				AS3Commons developers will make an effort to ensure that their components have
				minimal dependencies on other libraries, so that these components
				can be deployed easily. In addition, AS3Commons components will keep
				their interfaces as stable as possible, so that users (including
				other AS3Commons projects) can implement these components without
				having to worry about changes in the future.
			</p>
			<p>
				We welcome participation from all that are interested, at all skill
				levels. Coding, documentation and testing are all critical parts of
				the software development process. If you are interested in
				participating in any of these aspects, please join us!
			</p>
			<p>All libraries are also available in the Maven repository at
				<a href="http://projects.yoolab.org/maven/content/repositories/releases/org/as3commons" target="_blank">
					http://projects.yoolab.org/maven/content/repositories/releases/org/as3commons
				</a>
			</p>
			<subsection name="Projects">
				<table>
					<tr>
						<td align="center" width="150">
							<strong>Name</strong>
						</td>
						<td align="center">
							<strong>Description</strong>
						</td>
						<td align="center" width="100">
							<strong>Version</strong>
						</td>
						<td align="center" width="100">
							<strong>Last update</strong>
						</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>
							<strong><a href="as3-commons-async/index.html">Async</a></strong>
						</td>
						<td>A library that aims to make working with asynchronous processes easier. Providing operation,
							command, service and task interfaces.
						</td>
						<td>1.0.0-RC.2</td>
						<td>22 Mar 2012</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>
							<strong><a href="as3-commons-async-flex/index.html">Async Flex</a></strong>
						</td>
						<td>Includes an extra SWC with Flex extensions for the Async library.</td>
						<td>1.0.0-RC.2</td>
						<td>22 Mar 2012</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>
							<strong><a href="as3-commons-bytecode/index.html">Bytecode</a></strong>
						</td>
						<td>Bytecode parsing and publishing formerly known as Loom. Capable of generating classes at
							runtime, bytecode based reflection and more.
						</td>
						<td>1.1.1</td>
						<td>01 Apr 2012</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>
							<strong><a href="as3-commons-collections/index.html">Collections</a></strong>
						</td>
						<td>Collections framework including several lists, sets and maps, many of them in an additional
							bindable version.
						</td>
						<td>1.3.2</td>
						<td>19 Sep 2011</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>
							<strong><a href="as3-commons-eventbus/index.html">EventBus</a></strong>
						</td>
						<td>The EventBus is used as a publish/subscribe event mechanism that lets objects communicate
							with eachother in a loosely coupled way. It offers event subscription based on event name,
							event class or for specific topics. An interception mechanism is in place to block or alter
							incoming events or event listeners being added.
						</td>
						<td>1.3</td>
						<td>26 Mar 2012</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>
							<strong><a href="as3-commons-lang/index.html">Lang</a></strong>
						</td>
						<td>Language utilities and extensions.</td>
						<td>0.3.7</td>
						<td>24 May 2013</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>
							<strong><a href="as3-commons-logging/index.html">Logging</a></strong>
						</td>
						<td>An abstraction over logging framework implementations. Being a pure actionscript library it
							can be used for any Flash/Flex/AIR project. Its use is recommended for use with other
							libraries/framework trying to be logging framework agnostic.
						</td>
						<td>2.7</td>
						<td>14 Oct 2011</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>
							<strong><a href="as3-commons-metadata/index.html">Metadata</a></strong>
						</td>
						<td>Library providing a generic mechanism for intercepting and handling of custom metadata on
							actionscript instances and classes.
						</td>
						<td>1.0.1</td>
						<td>29 Mar 2012</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>
							<strong><a href="as3-commons-reflect/index.html">Reflect</a></strong>
						</td>
						<td>A reflection API for ActionScript 3.0. Being a pure actionscript library it can be used for
							any Flash/Flex/AIR project. It functions as a wrapper for the native describeType and
							describeTypeJSON methods. Results are statically cached to improve performance.
						</td>
						<td>1.6.3</td>
						<td>24 May 2013</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>
							<strong><a href="as3-commons-stageprocessing/index.html">Stage Processing</a></strong>
						</td>
						<td>A pure actionscript 3 library that provides an API for intercepting objects that have been
							added to or removed from the Flash stage.
						</td>
						<td>1.1.0</td>
						<td>22 Mar 2012</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>
							<strong><a href="as3-commons-ui/index.html">UI</a></strong>
						</td>
						<td>Algorithms and managers to serve common UI releated tasks such as layouting, focus and
							keyboard management, popup handling, drag and drop control and so on. All packages support
							native Flash display objects. Usage of UI does not require interface implementations. The
							first version (0.1) includes the sole layout package. Version 0.2 adds the Invalidation and
							LifeCycle package. Version 0.3 comes with popup and tooltip management.
						</td>
						<td>0.3.4</td>
						<td>19 Sep 2011</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>
							<strong><a href="as3-commons-zip/index.html">Zip</a></strong>
						</td>
						<td>A library to load, modify and create standard ZIP archives. It parses ZIP archives
							progressively, allowing access to contained files while the archive is loading.
						</td>
						<td>1.0.0-alpha.1</td>
						<td>29 Mar 2012</td>
					</tr>
				</table>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Dormant Projects">
				<p>These are AS3Commons projects that haven't been updated in a longer time.</p>
				<table>
					<tr>
						<td align="center" width="150">
							<strong>Name</strong>
						</td>
						<td align="center">
							<strong>Description</strong>
						</td>
						<td align="center" width="100">
							<strong>Version</strong>
						</td>
						<td align="center" width="100">
							<strong>Last update</strong>
						</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>
							<strong><a href="as3-commons-concurrency/index.html">Concurrency</a></strong>
						</td>
						<td>Pseudo-threading support.</td>
						<td>1.0-RC1</td>
						<td>09 Sep 2010</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>
							<strong><a href="as3-commons-serialization/index.html">Serialization</a></strong>
						</td>
						<td>XML Serialization library for ActionScript 3.0.</td>
						<td>0.1</td>
						<td>09 Sep 2010</td>
					</tr>
				</table>
			</subsection>
		</section>

	</body>
</document>

